<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Rails Girls | Ramon Huidobro]]></title>
  <link href="http://ramonh.github.io/blog/categories/rails-girls/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ramonh.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-21T18:08:07+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://ramonh.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Coaching at Rails Girls Vienna 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://ramonh.github.io/blog/2014/11/21/coaching-at-rails-girls-vienna/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-21T12:21:35+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://ramonh.github.io/blog/2014/11/21/coaching-at-rails-girls-vienna</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last weekend, I had my first experience in coaching at a Rails Girls event.</p>

<p>I loved every minute of it.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;ve ever wanted to try out web programming in a great environment, or help out, <a href="http://railsgirls.com/">what are you waiting for?</a> There are events all over the world!</p>

<!-- more -->


<p><img src="/images/rg-vie-2014.jpg" title="&lsquo;Rails Girls Vienna&rsquo;" >
<em>Many thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/railsgirls_vie/">@RailsGirls_VIE</a> for the photos!</em></p>

<p>The workshop was venue sponsored by Microsoft. It was a fascinating look into their HQ. There were rumblings of a slide, but we never checked it out!</p>

<p>The way a Rails Girls usually starts is with an Installation Party. <a href="https://twitter.com/althaire">@althaire</a> and I arrived early to help set stuff up, and then the attendees arrived.</p>

<p>We used <a href="http://nitrous.io/">Nitrous</a> for the workshop. If you haven&rsquo;t checked it out before, Nitrous is an online service to run, work on and deploy web apps. It&rsquo;s great because you&rsquo;re working on a remote linux instance. How cool is that!? This meant that the installation party consisted mostly of setting up a Nitrous account and getting to know the IDE (Integrated Development Environment) a little bit.</p>

<p>I took the opportunity to show some of the attendees around the command line interface. This is a section that I feel is often overlooked or even dismissed by people, despite its power. Maybe something to consider for a future post?</p>

<p>On the next day, after introductions and sponsor talks, we got to it! We started with the <a href="http://tryruby.org/">Try Ruby Tutorial</a>. I like it! It&rsquo;s almost like an IRB instance, but it kind of carries you along as you learn Ruby. The later levels get a little oddly difficult, but it&rsquo;s definitely a good way to get started.</p>

<p>After getting our feet wet with Ruby, we dove straight into Rails with Nitrous. The guides come in <a href="http://guides.railsgirls.com/">several languages</a> and are really nice!</p>

<p>After a delicious lunch (I had sushi!) it was time for the lightning talks!</p>

<p><img src="/images/rg-vie-2014-2.jpg" title="&lsquo;Rails Girls Vienna&rsquo;" >
<em><a href="https://twitter.com/althaire">@althaire</a> talking about where to go next after Rails Girls.</em></p>

<p>We started with @althaire talking about where to go next, where she proposed starting a Ruby and Rails learning group in Vienna. I&rsquo;ll be sure to help out with organizing in any way I can.</p>

<p>Next, came <a href="https://twitter.com/alicetragedy">@alicetragedy</a> with a great talk on breaking rules and other things beautifully. Very inspiring stuff!</p>

<p>Next was me! I gave a short talk on the importance of taking a break when stuck in anything, including programming. You can find the slides, complete with silly drawings, <a href="https://speakerdeck.com/ramonh/stuck-take-a-break">here</a>.</p>

<p>Finally we learned about CryptoParties from <a href="https://twitter.com/meep_vie">@meep_vie</a>. Very interesting! I&rsquo;ll have to check them up.</p>

<p>After completing the workshop, including some fun with deploying to <a href="https://www.heroku.com/">Heroku</a>, styling with CSS and doing the follow-up tutorials, I&rsquo;d say the workshop was a success!</p>

<p>The best part was finding out that some of the attendees were already making stuff the next day!</p>

<p>I got to meet some people and take a step further into being active in the community.</p>

<p>I can only hope to do it again soon. In fact, I will! I&rsquo;ll be coaching at <a href="http://railsgirls.com/bratislava">Rails Girls Bratislava</a> in December.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
